[Music]
so maybe yeah I'd like to like in a way
formally begin the conversation now but
obviously everything we can use
everything from behind and so maybe just
so for some context for people that are
potentially watching this I released a
video about Jordan Peterson and it was a
I suppose in an attempt to make sense of
him by comparing and contrasting him
with Russell Brand and these are two
figures who are on one level deeply
spiritual but are often points maybe of
an ideological spectrum and we can
explore maybe their nuance of that and
it was my attempt as was having come
from a left-wing background and
identifying as progressive to try and
bring an open-minded perspective on
peterson and and using kind of clips
from Russell Brand and Jordan Peterson's
discussions as a kind of a way to
illuminate that and they've got a I
think I've got a pretty good response I
got eighty thousand views and I think
for me it's signals I desire for a
response particularly from the left that
was more than automatic dismissal and
demonizing Peterson but actually being
able to say this is what's good about
and this is what maybe is problematic
and I and so that that happened and then
and a couple of weeks later you sent me
an email saying I wrote a critique of
your essay or of the video and my
immediate response was kind of to go
into that slightly panicked mode about
what you might have said because I read
the critique that you wrote of Jonathan
Robbins essay and and found that yeah a
penetrating analysis in the sense that
it wasn't just playing the ideas but it
was actually diving into maybe some of
the psychology of the the author or the
person but anyways I'm a tree and the
Enneagram
which is very achievable image-conscious
and so I I carry a lot of that just fear
of how people think of me or what they
may think of means that this is their
kind of a sensitive territory but the
other thing in terms of bringing the
personal dimension in that I found
interesting was that I had already
warmed to you as a writer and thinker
because one of your pieces on the
devouring mother which was written about
broadly you know the shadow of the left
also helped me with family dynamics that
I was experiencing on a trip back home
to rural Ireland so already there was
this sense of I suppose an appreciation
and an affinity which I suppose allowed
me to be more receptive and I think
these things are quite on one level sort
of but actually quite important for it
to be able to have a dialogue that there
is kind of this sense of generosity and
willingness so there's a bridge on which
you can have it so I just wanted to name
that maybe the background to the things
that were going on in the background
that maybe informs our conversation
which I feel has been productive so far
mm-hmm okay well that's those two those
two poles right the devouring mother and
the tyrannical father our articulations
of Peterson right which he get he gets
from young and new men and all that and
what what I've been seeing right in in
them and the culture in general and in
the reaction to to Peterson is let's say
fear of the tyrannical father and which
I think goes along with the election of
Trump I mean if you think of two figures
today who are two male figures who are
more prevalent in the culture you would
say Trump and Peterson and I kind of see
them on opposite poles the father is
such a threatening figure in in
postmodern culture and that two people
on the Left that this is this is the
this is the reason for all the extreme
polarized you know reaction to Peterson
and I think that that maybe was the
the core I felt of the Crips T my video
which was that I set up a problem which
was that we live in a polarized culture
we are forced to take positions on
Peterson before him or against him and
this reduces the complexity and then as
you rightly point out there is a an
obvious irony in while I do way up
Peterson and brand at the end I come
down with a criticism from a progressive
perspective and say you know like I
close the video by saying that you know
we can't afford this type of thinking
right now where we are and I think that
it's a really it's a really spot-on
criticism and it's one that I was aware
of as I was doing it and I think that
maybe just to share what was going on
for me that led me to do that and
because I I think that um I am within a
very left-wing progressive circle in
London where you know there was quite a
strong queer LGBTQ community and you
know these are my friends these are the
people I see at parties and so similar
to do any association with Peterson that
is that wasn't rejecting did carry a
fear of being out grouped and it does
you know and as you you reference Jordan
green Noel's articles that you know that
that is a very personal thing you're not
seen as a good social ally you're not
seen as a good you know sexual partner
it's at that level of rejection you know
and and well that's precisely did the
devouring mother which doesn't allow you
and have an individual point of view
right it doesn't allow you to have a
heterodox or a point of view is because
you're devoured by the by the tribalism
right you you can't stand out or you're
in danger actually
yeah and and I think this so I really
you know I really felt this big anxiety
about doing a piece on Peterson and and
wanted on one level to bring this meta
modern perspective where we could really
say yes and to Peterson like what is
what are the good things that he's
bringing but also felt a lot of pressure
it was internal pressure
it was my pitch elation to the tribal
block to kind of come down in a critical
fashion and I think it's just I think
that's an interesting thing to kind of
maybe make visible and make public is
that I felt a lot of anxiety and coming
down coming down with a constructive
criticism was a way of relating that and
ultimately I did feel a strong pressure
to display loyalty to my in-group yeah
at the same time it's not as simple as
you know I did it from a place of fear I
also genuinely believe that his
characterization of post-modernism is a
bit of a straw man that he
over-exaggerates the fears of collective
action and all of those things I also
believe but in there is more going on
beneath the surface and I think that
what I'm finding in this conversational
space that were in is that were
surfacing in a true psychological sense
the thing behind the thing so yeah we
have our arguments about issues but
actually what's going in beat the
surface it's my fear of you know people
having a go of me the next party that I
matched because I don't criticize
Peterson strongly enough for you know
his view climate change or Trump or
women right so yeah be interested to get
your reflection on that and is are there
maybe any reference points that might
enrich that well I you know if you if
you if you listen to his discussion with
with Russell Brand which I thought was a
great discussion by the way I thought
they both they both were able to have a
conversation a fruitful and enriching
conversation with
out being for or against each other and
and yet coming from from from different
perspectives and I think that's the
subtle that's the subtle if that was my
criticism is is that is that well that
you you seem to be taking you seem to be
pushing forward a conciliatory message
at the same time you still seem to have
this this this let's say for our against
position that you seem to need to to
express so can i I said one thing that
came up for me was this tension between
both and and really you know it was your
contention that if you really wanted to
be meta modern to really just integrate
you know both perspectives Russell Brand
and Jordan Peterson's and then just
allow that to be rather than coming down
on one side but then also I suppose
because we obviously you know these
ideas operate within a context of them
informing real policy decisions that
affect people's lives and and I suppose
I one of the one of my responses to you
over email was you know if we're in an
ad like okay so there's a problem of
polarization but we do live in an
adversarial political climate where
there is a battle of ideas and and this
battle informs policy choices but what
we do in climate change what we do in
housing policy how we think about
immigration and where is the room while
still holding an appreciation for other
ideas to actually come down on one side
and actually say no like this this is
wrong and we should we shouldn't listen
as much to this person as we do and we
should remember the virtue and value of
post-modernism or left-wing perspectives
and then a lot of a lot of you know a
lot of people who you know criticized a
lot of let's say friends in the left who
criticize my video and the interview I
did with David fuller and Revolution
would say that you're you're in giving
cover - Jordan Peterson you're also
giving cover - you know the far right or
who might use his ideas as intellectual
cover for a right-wing agenda that's
really spreading and growing so I just
wanted to maybe that was kind of cool he
expressed but I wanted just to bring
bring that and get your thoughts on that
I don't think there's any evidence that
Peterson is far right I think there's
there's there's no evidence for that and
I think there is some evidence that he's
a bit of a conservative uh-huh and I'm
not a conservative I've never I've never
felt like a conservative on the other
hand I think that what what he what what
he what he does is he brings people who
have a conservative bent let's say a
conservative to a position that that's
that's that's more that's more and
reasonable and and more and more
centered so I think he's bringing a lot
of the wingnuts you know from the far
right you know into into a more
reasonable position he allows me to view
conservatism traditionalism with with
more compassion than I did before and I
think that's an interesting one because
again it's the it's the background
context that informs maybe your position
so to share mine
I very much been in the systems change
space that's been my the work that I've
done that's been my agenda is you know
transitioning from what I would see as a
you know a you know for all its virtues
and its ability to lift millions out of
poverty is still a very extractive
system and trying to move to something
that is more fit for purpose for the
future and and so I said I suppose maybe
I see a lot of this these ideas is what
utility they have for my political
agenda and and that probably does
obscure my ability to truly enter into a
liminal space to truly hold an unknowing
position and to want to maybe Corral
people around a certain set of
perspectives and positions and I think
that it may be a penny is just wrong for
me as you speak that
implicit in a lot of Pearson's talks and
lectures and debates is this resistance
to being corralled by a group consensus
that might be prevalent at the time
mm-hmm and that is an embodiment of the
kind of the sovereign individual who
will make up their own mind and will say
what they think and yeah and I suppose
in a way he is modeling that I'm curious
about in a way at least I 62 and there
might be more pathways but one
traditional political pathway is you
know it's a binary it's left versus
right years you you know advance your
ideas as best you can of the political
space and you affect change and and that
when someone comes along from you know
even if it's the moderate right that's
that feels threatening to those ideas
and so you try and dismiss them or take
them down and and then there's this what
feels like a new political space opening
which is about integrating and
transcending so this kind of approach
informed by integral theory or meta
modernism and the it's an attempt to
really see the virtue of the healthy
expression of the other side so the
healthy expression of the masculine on
the right or the individual on the right
and that maybe is there is an assumption
that if there is some degree of
generosity to the what was considered an
opposing perspective that will also be
met with generosity and that we might be
able to find a new space of civic
dialogue in the middle where our both
our conversation and our policy choices
have some sense of balance and the you
know at a personal level and energetic
level of the balance between the
feminine and the masculine on a policy
level between stage and market and that
we're looking at maybe a what you might
call a deeper center or a more
productive center that isn't just based
on
wherever like wherever the war of ideas
leaves us on the ideological perspective
but it's actually actively co-created
and and participated in and and so my
and that's basically the maybe
assumption that I've been following and
maybe my I have doubts about that
because even if one side capitulates for
example but we're not capitulated even
if one side really honors and recognizes
the virtue of Peters in their virtue of
the right that doesn't necessarily mean
that the right will honor and integrate
the virtues of the left actually you
might just be a conventional political
understanding ceding ground to just a
more right-wing understanding in view
and so that's my I think that that's
maybe one of my concerns is that you
know it you can enter into a dialogue
and hopefully that would be meshed with
reciprocity but there's always you know
actors within a political game that are
just ruthlessly advancing their
interests and you know if I am if I'm
let's say the Koch brothers or if I am
really advancing a particular right-wing
neoliberal agenda it it might entirely
play into my game to have this emerging
ecosystem of people like me and you who
are entering into this integral space
and honoring the ideas of the right but
at the same time they advance their
agenda so that's maybe that's a concern
that I have and I'm very very curious to
get your your thoughts on that well I
think what I hear is that you're afraid
of losing some kind of ground and my
question would be where is the ground
you know I mean is there a ground I mean
in one in one sense yes there is we have
a divided brain you know we're divided
within ourselves we have a left and you
know our left brain functions
differently than our right brain so part
of us is very protective and
conservative and
that doesn't want to step into you know
difficult difficult this difficult
liminal space and and part of a part of
us is dying for four you know I think in
one of your talk to you talked about you
know this vulnerability and where you
feel alive right so so I think that's
that's the that's the place to be right
the place to be is in this vulnerable
space where you feel alive it's it's not
to be to be have a fixed agenda or fixed
position or a fixed you know point of
view but again I hear what you're saying
you know if you're too much in this
middle space maybe it all turns to mush
and you know you know don't want to you
don't know what to do or you don't know
what particular you know if you're in
the political world you don't know what
particular you know you know policy to
support well but it's interesting to me
like I think we I think you're I also
something I hear what you're saying is
you're looking for combat and combat is
important but combat combat in the sense
of non-violent combat because there has
to be combat you know there's a combat
of nature to to our to our spirit which
is a thing of beauty and that's that the
masculinity right which is so so
repressed in a conciliatory space right
so so you know combat but you know I
hate to over quote Peterson but minimal
necessary force right so does that make
sense sense to you
like what I find often is is in a much
of the leftist discussion is this sort
of machinist yeah this kind of you know
being vulnerable and being open and
being you know but what if they're not
vulnerable and open to you know they're
gonna crush you right so yes you need
your you need your armor but but also
but also you need to be able to you know
you need your armor and you need to be
vulnerable you need to be you know the
samurai in the masculine need a strong
masculine force but you also need you
know the yogi combines the feminine and
the masculine in one person you also
need this you know loving tender you
know
compassion you know all these you know
whatever the feminine is which is often
you know expressed in cliches right
because the feminine also has a fierce
element to it but so can we just know
just just because I think there's
something I'd like to to go into in a
second but so you said that either you
noticed in me a fear of ceding ground
the true place to be is in the liminal
and in the vulnerable and I would say I
I definitely agree with that and I do
believe that genuine political
resolution comes from both sides
entering into that space and actually
what wants to emerge comes through both
being willing to cede their fixed
positions and the new being born through
that dialogical process but at the same
time not all actors in the system are
subscribed to that game but subscribed
to advancing their fixed-point agenda
and what I see is a wider phenomenon and
you can you commit correct you think may
interrupt you though just for a second
maybe that see the ground is if you're
you're you're you're you're you're too
concerned about what all the other
actors are about right or maybe it's
just pragmatic you know maybe it's just
political survival I don't know does
that make any sense
well well maybe well maybe I'll
illustrate with an example and then you
can you can reflect back to me what
you're seeing or what maybe I'm not
seeing so I see a a broader phenomenon
in the rise of the or Trice of you know
a moral a moral panic about free speech
and an over inflation of the harms of
post-modernism a pathologizing of the
social justice warrior and what I see is
a discrediting of civic and social
justice movements that I think are
really necessary at this they're always
necessary in society to have movements
for social justice and that they play a
very
function in promoting as I see the real
threat of climate change
the real trash of fascist nationalist
governments and - and and you know in
terms of where the world is going and
you know I see a very clear correlation
between you know climate change and
resource scarcity mass migration and the
rise of authoritarianism of the loss of
the liberal order so that is that is a
political game that's playing out and
within that from my perspective at a
time when the left and movements for
liberalism and for and for greater
fairness and equality and action and
climate change are needed we see what
feels like a demonization of those
forces and yes those forces absolutely
need to acknowledge their shadow and the
devouring mother that is creating this
problem but I'm also just aware of you
know with someone like Peterson I whose
agenda does Peterson support or whose
agenda is furthered by by Peterson being
a being public intellectual and yeah so
maybe that's the ground what I think
about and I do think it's a matter of
political survival I do really see a
threat of the the far right being that
the preeminent political force of the
21st century yeah but with the far left
you know they really are they're they're
they're almost the same beast you know
because the more the more the the
far-left pushes that pushes the the
buttons of the far right that the more
polarized those those two groups become
so this is exactly that the you know
Trump is the exact result of you know
this this group of people who were very
condescending to traditional working
people right who treated them like
deplorable human beings and and and
considered themselves to be superior in
all ways right so so you know you know
these you know so so these the work
you know working people need a voice I
mean and a voice is not an intellectual
they don't need a I don't know what it's
just it's an energetic thing too as well
as an intellectual game you might have
all the right answers but people don't
vote with their their minds they you
know really I mean do they I mean the
average guy average person yeah it's a
woman and in America are they voting
with with with with intellect no they're
voting with their their guts right so
there's an integration that that the
left and I think Peterson is very
helpful to the left he may be even more
helpful to the left and he used to the
right I mean because because he's
allowing for a lot of people are like
are left this but they're they're
they're you know they've been listening
to Peterson their land they're kind of
leftist and they're afraid to tell their
friends they're listening to Peters to
them but you know I think I think I
think he's helping to integrate maybe a
healthy version of conservatism in the
culture or giving that a voice as well
which is which is necessary you know
yeah I totally see that the Petersons
wasn't properly received is a gap is a
gift for the left because he's a mirror
to the shadow of the left and it's only
by under like being able to have
conversations about for example near the
archetype of the devouring mother that
the left can actually win more people
over because at the moment the
unintegrated shadow is basically putting
people off and then fueling the fire
right so I have an idea
I want to I have an idea I want I want
to throw out at you related to the
shadow stuff right because everybody's
talking about the shadow right these
days and I had the idea here I thought
that okay what is the shadow of the mass
flame right everybody says it's it's
it's violence and aggression and you
know all the terrible things that you
know men have done through history and
so so we the the the outer view is that
that the shadow of the masculine is
aggression right and in and and
shadow of the feminine is then is then
passivity you could say or being
invisible or or are not stepping up or
that kind of thing so you have this
passion you have this aggression shadow
and then you have this
passive-aggressive shadow but then I
also and then I thought it's the reverse
right the shadow of the masculine is
passive aggression uh-huh is not
becoming fully masculine and the shadow
of the of the feminine is aggression
which you see very much and hitting me
to movement aggression against men it's
the part that you don't want to admit or
seeing yourself right so women don't
want to admit that they have this
aggressive aspect to that to their
natures and men don't want to you know
men don't men become men men have this I
don't know I men have this what men have
this tendency to vacillate it and not
you know fully embody their masculinity
and and and and and and even their
aggression so so anyway that was just
something I was thinking about which I
wanted to fill I mean I totally I did
I totally I I see both and I see it in
myself you know can you can you fully
step into an own and express your maths
and power in the world and to what
degree given the prevailing culture do
we feel a hyper self-consciousness about
that because it's associated with Turney
and I was aggression and despite that
can you still stand in your truth and
stand on your power and and express that
and I think that's yeah I really
resonate with that and I also um I'm
encouraged well at least I can only
speak from our high circles but more and
more I'm seeing a willingness to speak
about the shadow feminine and the the
ways in which women you know can be
manipulative er can deceive or can
display aggression and how that is
showing off in the me to conversation
for example I don't know if you saw the
the video the camera
me which was a series of women
apologizing to men for aspects of the
shadowing of her and you know there was
there was you know there was criticisms
that video of you know you can apologize
on behalf of the gender to another
gender you can only own what you've done
personally but there was I think it was
interesting in that it marked a shift in
the conversation you know the the
prevailing cultural understanding is you
know men have done wrong and women are
the victims of that yeah have to go
beyond victimology as being the first
know there are real victims but you have
to go beyond victimology as being the
first impulse uh-huh and and and self
responsibility on both sides you know I
meant masculine side and feminine side
I'm curious too
do you have that's so do you have a
sense that a genuine resolution is
possible or obviously there will always
be tensions and conflict within you know
large scale systems and societies over
ideas but do you feel like there could
be the birth of this more integrated
center where you know you even have
political parties that are the
institutional embodiment of being able
to hold the masculine and the feminine
attack on a cultural level be able to
honor left and right wing ideas and that
would gather eyes enough people around
that to keep maybe leave more on
integrated extremes of the left and
right or the unintegrated extremes of
masculine feminine at bay and that there
would be a kind of a center that could
hold us you do have confidence in that
confidence know a certain amount of hope
yes
I I think that I think you to a certain
kind of utopianism is dangerous um
because you're living for the future
more than you're living you know
appreciating you know the complexity and
messiness of the of the current
situation so so I I don't think
resolution is what we should be looking
for you know I don't think we should be
looking for resolution I think we should
be looking to be become more alive and
embodied as people and and have more
meaningful lives so so I don't I don't
hold out much hope for any collective
again I guess that makes me a Peter
Sounion in some sense is it's the
sovereignty of the individual but i but
i but I also think that I also think
that society organically grows towards
that does that make any sense we'll just
say a bit more I was with you into the
last sentence and you said society
organic he grows towards that well I
think that there's there is you know I
think I think that there's an organic
growth of of society that happens at the
same time as it falls apart like the two
are so simultaneously happening so it
gets worse and worse and worse and worse
and worse
and then there's this sort of light
shining in the darkness that gets
brighter and brighter and brighter and
brighter
yeah yeah I mean that resonates I see
the the seeds of that emerging or you
know the source code of that and
and maybe it just so happens that the
has more airtime or feels louder you
know it's more of the mainstream
institutions and kind of mainstream
ecological figures or maybe an
embodiment of that like Trump being an
example but then you also have this
emerging in yeah point of integration
and I think this is I think what's
interesting is that it feels very
mystical and very spiritual in at its
core that it is this very deeply
personal process of understanding the
ways in which you need to grow in order
to see with greater clarity the
complexity of what's happening to be
able to meet people with greater empathy
to be able to forge something that works
better on a more complex level so yeah
this this like phrase the personal is
political I think is taking them to a
meaning in in this time that we're in
mm-hmm yeah this is okay I've been
trying to understand what Metta
modernism is and I understand that you
work with many modernist concepts and
and I think the one of the ideas of meta
modernism is that this integrate include
the include idea is its its political
and i-i-i don't think how do i say this
i don't think it starts from the
political I think it starts from the the
the trance the inner transformation
I don't think societies you know like
this this idea I guess there's an
economist named shoemaker who had this
book called small as beautiful and the
idea that so it starts very small I went
to yeah I know just to say that I went
to Schumacher College they're very
influenced by oh yeah yeah well I mean
that this phrase works for me it makes
sense to me because a real community is
small it can't be big right because as
soon as something gets too big it loses
its it's human
contours there's there's no intimacy
between people so so that's that's where
actually that's where I have if I have
hope or something it would be in small
communities not in big social movements
III distrust maybe it's my personality I
distrust big big social movements but I
think if you have a lot of small
movements which are spiritually grounded
and intelligent then then that lifts the
society up and yeah well the last thing
I wanted to say is that I think that has
to be expressed maybe in mythopoetic
terms in the arts as well so there has
to be it has to happen on all kinds of
levels right it has to happen
simultaneously on all kinds of levels
and for me the political is the last
level so I was surprised at MIT and
modernist as a sort of emphasis in the
political freak because for me I always
think of the political sort of the last
yeah level but yeah I think that maybe
like my understanding from working with
meta modernists and being a part of that
conversation is yeah the key idea is
that personal growth through personal
development is the route to a you know a
strong and stable Society so it is very
much beginning with the eye but it's
acknowledging that the ways in which
those ideas take wholes are at a
cultural level and that the way there
may be reinforced supported is by policy
and political institutions and so they
would be like for example one of the
core ideas is this idea of welfare state
2.0 which isn't just providing a kind of
a material security it's also assisting
people on their journey of psychological
development and of course you know that
can get you into strange totalitarian
places when you have systems that are is
that are that are supporting on that
level but I do think that's a question
of maybe method and policy design but
the basic I think the basic premise is
sound I think that politics in a way of
in terms of where we are on the
trajectory of the ideas were very much
as I as far as I can see it
in that this is an emerging subculture
where a personal growth is really the
Paramount and we see a lot of ideas in
the online cultural space that are
reflecting that and that it probably
does best to take root within small
tribes you know that you you can't do
personal growth work on your own you
need a Sangha you need a community that
can hold you to account that can support
you and you know I see them in my in my
own you know London hipster subculture
where you know that is self-organized
you know I mean the co-working spaces
the psychedelic society there's nothing
political or staged related about that
that's the self-organized community an
organization that you know obviously are
using psychedelics is a particular
method or two but they're at the bases
is its self-organizing for people to
practice personal growth become better
versions of themselves I do think that
you know someone someone friend of mine
Sarah's old fat jokes alter-ego the
organization I run we organize
gatherings that are bringing you know
leaders in the progressive space around
these ideas and to and you know our
strap line is deep politics for divided
times but but she was saying that the
mission of the organization should be
that in the future it's as easy to get a
personal development loan as it is to
get a business loan and and obviously
the joke and that is that we clearly
have policy that favors certain
priorities and certain goals and if we
are if we really believe in these ideas
and policy on some level should be
supporting them that should be it you
know and I do know that there is a
culture of personal growth you know and
like you know Peterson's ideas are
really central in this that are
reflected in policy so I don't see there
being attention in in less a meta
modernism being a political project my
work is coercion in that case you know
my worry is
it's just it's just the kind of worry
you if you said people relate to
personal growth camps or whatever you
know this you know personal growth is a
very delicate organic you know complex
process and I would be afraid that it
would be corrupted by too much
institutionalization but then you know
at the same time if we think like
personal growth has always been
emphasized maybe not in the in its
Dilbert kind of spiritual connotation
now but like the whole idea of character
development of certain values being in
stairs and populations it's like that's
that's that's entirely coercive that is
a society on some level deciding how it
wants to condition itself and that
process is happening regardless and so
the question is what does agency looked
like within it like how can we promote a
set of values at a collective level that
are about personal growth and that also
really emphasizes twenty of the
individual to question that process that
like really emphasizes critical thinking
and a rebellious spirit or whatever that
might be so I don't think we can lower
age collective conditioning we're doing
it you know we're doing it in a
self-organized
collective way regardless and yeah we
are a collective beings I mean most of
us we believe that we're individuals but
you know if we really examined our mind
a you know we're governed by super-ego
of the society and I think real
collective growth is a process of
developing something but it's also it's
also dismantling that collective
coercion so just an idea that has come
to me now I'm really in this idea of the
collective super-ego and I haven't I
haven't really heard of this as a phrase
and and it makes a lot of sense in the
way that our own privates super-ego
restrains us with
a kind of a barrage of thoughts that
keeps us in our box that happens in a
collective level and it feels like a lot
of the commentary in the online space is
about the devouring mother collective
super-ego you know this particular
censorship this kind of crowd-sourced
collective censorship of ideas and
thoughts and the way you're supposed to
think about climate change or the
patriarchy or whatever well equally I
and I wonder whether there's one coming
from the tyrannical folder of you know
hierarchical organization of a real
emphasis on you know corporatism and
business which is also conditioning a
particular type of productive worker and
particular values around self-worth that
a lot of people find it very difficult
to emancipate themselves from they find
it very difficult to exist the
collective folder of shadow of proving
yourself by being a good worker and I
just maybe I just want to look at your
reflections and whether there's a
devouring mother within the tyrannical
folder collective super-ego it's a
question of consciousness right so so
that the tyrannical father operates when
when he's he's uh he's unconscious and
the tyrannical mother operates when the
real when the good mother is is is is
unconscious so so so I think it's really
a question of consciousness so of course
you can see the tyrannical father
operating you know I have a daughter
she's nine years old and I can feel the
tyrannical father rising up in me at
times right you know and I can also feel
the devouring mother which is so hyper
for protective of this child that I
wouldn't want her to you know you know
IIIi wouldn't want her to walk a block
by herself in a city street you know so
so so so these are upper these are
operational on the microcosmic level and
also in society absolutely yeah we can
we can certainly you know criticize the
tyrannical father of
of Business and Finance and this
heartless aggression absolutely I mean
and we can also see we can also see this
hyper protective safeSpace culture which
Peterson goes on about you know Ignasi
right we're you know this you know we
have you always have to be you know you
always have to say the right thing and
whereas you know love is love love moves
in both directions right it moves
towards danger you you have to be able
to you know you have to be I wrote this
thing I was like safe space for being
dangerous because you have to be
dangerous like that's and if the space
is just safe then it's a sterile space
hmm but but it but but if but if it's
not protected it so so I think it's it's
always it's really this this is this
middle way you know as the Buddhists say
right this yeah not too tight not too
loose to to quote another Buddhist
cliche back just a lot of Buddhism so
have endless Zen cliches like not one
and not two right so it's this nor that
right it's neither you know match you
know you don't want a hyper masculine
model which is which is which is
absolutely you know a society based in
violence you don't want a hyper-feminine
model which is a society based on
castration you know clearly I was I was
reading this book of Newman and if you
look in ancient societies it's just
amazing how many castration cults there
there were in these ancient societies
and I was thinking when it went when a
lot of the the media operates and
Twitter operates as a sort of castration
you know cults you know it's like it's
like don't say this it's it's it's it's
it's no it's it's you know you're not
allowed to say that right so so so you
you end up becoming very small and
and very limited in your expression and
then and I suppose yeah I totally I
totally hear that and then I think the
the impulse behind that I mean there's
there's probably there's definitely a
shadow but the benevolent impulse behind
that is protective so that if certain
ideas are given licensed in society that
are harmful to groups that have less
power but that's a dangerous thing and
the impulse is to you know Corral a
certain conversational space to protect
that and you know as we're yeah maybe
just acknowledging the virtue behind
that or the at least in the prevalent
intention behind that is that if we so
like you know let's say when it comes to
points of view that might be considered
anti-semitic let's say this is the
current controversy going on the Labour
Party in the left there is a definite
you could say the devouring mother
archetype is present in saying you can't
have certain oh yeah points the new
absolute because you're you are creating
political space to be antisymmetric and
Jews will suffer because yes well maybe
that's what the devouring mother maybe
that's the the the the nurturing mother
you know this is you know that's that's
the positive mother mother role or or
the positive father right switch these
things around but but yeah but but but
right there's a limit right there's
there is a limit somewhere what I do
what I do what I do
maybe what I'm finding as you speak with
this middle way you know it's not it's
it's both it's becoming conscious of the
chronical father and the benevolent
mother it's it's this kind of
integration or this dynamic interplay
between the two where you say radical
father and the benevolent mother and the
devouring mother yeah maybe that's my
bias that's
that's your left-wing bias right there
right the mother is always is always
good you know and the father the
patriarchy the tyrannical father is
always you know bad you know yeah thank
you for calling me out on it sorry I'm
good I couldn't resist it but yeah but
like that's okay I think also it's okay
to to make a slip up that's your bias
and to and I and I think that to be
gently corrected and for that to be okay
you know that that's part of the I hope
that's part of the new political
discourse you know like we currently
live in a discourse where that kind of
thing is seized upon that's like I told
you he's a Marxist left yeah we
shouldn't listen to him rather than like
he's a young man trying to make his way
in the world and figure out what's what
and is full of biases which is I think
maybe a more positive rendering of who I
am and what I am and which is why I
really appreciated your writing because
I felt that generosity of like it's okay
it's like I see biases in this person
and I also have biases and that's okay
you know well and you also obviously
care for all these issues deeply right
you care for us you know women's issues
deeply right so so so and that causes
pain that's painful you have to take in
all this pain if you care about things
deeply right yeah so going back before I
made that slip-up father and the
devouring mother I'm having a deeper
appreciation that to maintain that space
at a collective level requires real
sovereignty of the individual because
you can't follow a collective script you
have to judge moment moment context to
context what's appropriate and have on
growing awareness of where you might be
slipping into the shadows the super-ego
right which is which is always
threatening to control you and you know
yeah some some kind of a box whereas
whereas the difficulty is
keeping remaining and that you use this
word vulnerable a lot remaining in this
in this intense vulnerability right
which is you know you want to shut down
you wanna you wanna you want to you want
to remain comfortable within your your
knowledge or certain to your ideology or
your tribe your family what you want
this discomfort which is important to
which I can go ahead no just to say that
I maybe I have a a maybe a new
understanding that politics in a way is
as is currently being played out is a
battle for the script for the collective
script that then polices people at a
collective level whether that the script
have left-wing or right-wing values that
it's a it's a battle over how we tell
people how to be and I think that what's
seeing is actually a rejection of that
process and of whether it whether it be
dominated by right-wing values or
left-wing values that actually what has
been cultivated is a sovereign
individual that the relationship with
the ego whether the individual or
collective level and it's not just the
sufferer an individual it's the I thou
relationship no rather than the I each
relationship if you know Martin Buber he
is a Jewish philosopher and he says you
know that what's most precious is this
space between us right it's not it's not
me as an individuals and you as an
individual it's it's it's the the space
of communication between us is that each
person you meet is a vow right and not
at it you know it's not a thing where
you know so so yeah I was thinking about
this idea of sovereign individuality and
I was thinking it's a very satisfying
concept but it also needs this
relational idea as well I did which is
it also needs it also needs this idea of
the when you meet in this
you know I guess the whole entire
political dialogue process etc is is
about that it's about meeting in this
in-between space right yeah and and and
and that's the only place where
something generative really happens yeah
otherwise we're just in our corner and
angry you pissed off or just just shut
down yeah yeah it reminds me of that you
know there's different models for
different levels of listening there is
the you know pure not listening where
you're just sticking with your fixed
viewpoint and rejecting and and and not
acknowledging either the other coast are
their ideas and then there's listening
it at the level of debate where I'll
share my thoughts you share your
thoughts will trash them out but
ultimately were coming from that and
then there's dialogue where were in some
level and a process of synthesis which
maybe I feel it's what we're displaying
here to greater an answer expense but
then the level below that is presencing
and that actually both of us in a kind
of a this is maybe more of like a
bohmian dialogue where we are feeling
into what wants to be generated from
between Venus in the conversational
space what is the new that wants to
emerge and and and and trusting that in
the intelligence of that but it's
neither your idea of my idea it's the
space between well that's what you feel
in any body right that's that that's
when it's no longer in merely
intellectual it's that you feel it on a
really somatic level I think when you
get to the presence of things
so do you feel maybe what's alive from
for you now having we arrived at that
place I think that this is a positive
and yeah it's it's but there is there is
for me always because it maybe it's just
because of my personality there there's
always there there is always this you
know uncertainty or groundless Nesser
it's like where are we you know right
now but I'm familiar with that because I
practiced meditation quite a bit I
haven't mastered it Miami means I'm but
but I'm familiar with that with we're
doing that that kind of work on some
level hmm so what I what I notice in
myself is both I feel as we talk more
embodied I feel like a greater
spaciousness in my body and um there's a
curiosity about what emerges from that
space between us that I can probably
only locate by speaking about what's
going on inside me and you know whether
that be feelings or thoughts and I I
really feel like this conversation has
meaning for me even though I feel like
there's been a dynamic of a kind of a
teacher students happening here I feel
like a you know a lot of the views that
I'm bringing your I suppose like my
being to attend agogic and they're not
in a way that's in a way this humble
and good and it's I don't know it's I I
I find this it's it's both it's really
opening my eyes to perspectives and
there's also humility required in that
and and I and I then I have this
lingering devouring mother collected
super-ego telling me that I'm straying
away from my progressive doctrine you
know and I just want to acknowledge that
you know what to be conscious of that I
somehow feel very probably the which i
think is quite natural when you record
something and put something online yeah
the fear of but what will people think
of this what will people make of this
will you know and I just want to bring
that into the conversation of space that
that's a that's an aspect of my
experience as we talk and that's maybe
that's what's the live for me is as I go
further from what I know and from my own
script which is you know has been
developed within myself but is obviously
informed by the collective I I'm more
and more entered into this unknown space
which feels like both alive and
uncomfortable but I but it's I also have
a sense of meaning in that that that's
that actually people what people are
searching for or at least what some
people are searching for is that it's
like don't tell me don't give me the
talking points and the rehearsal points
the left versus right I've heard them
I'm done with them I I want to be in the
space of unknown with you and see what
what arises yeah and what what we're
looking for is we're looking for a
living a living speech right we're
looking we're looking to be able to
really speak to each other beyond
truisms and cliches and and and these
these automatic reflexes that we have
and you know and whatever indoctrination
you know we you know we that has been
imposed on us we want what
when you when you have real
communication you're very close to
poetry right because you're expressing
what is coming up right now it's it's
very different than than an argument or
I think you spoke about that a few
minutes ago it's not it's not an
argument it's it's it's an unraveling
and a revealing process you know I read
Heidegger and I and and Heidegger talks
about thinking thought as being it's
something revealed it's not it's not a
concept it's not it's not it's not it's
not something delineated it's when
something is is something unfold
something is you know something is
unfolding and that yeah that's the
liminal uncomfortable you know difficult
space and and that's what we have to
have to keep doing or we're gonna die
you know we're just beginning to become
what dirt-cheap called machine man you
know we're we're completely you know we
can become very robotic people we can we
can become very you know we can just
completely we can but completely
mechanized recognized people unless we
make this effort to enter this
uncomfortable space right so I feel the
same way as you I feel that talking to
you
III I do feel I'm entering into a
discomfort of some kind because you know
I don't know you and one thing that's
coming up for me is that I've been
invited to give a talk in Vienna in a
couple of weeks time on vulnerability in
21st century politics something like
that and and in many ways our
conversation is validating that
hypothesis that if we genuinely want to
produce something new and not recreate
old patterns that we have to enter into
this vulnerable space together that's
kind of the maybe the core of it but
then my question is is a lot of but a
lot of vulnerability is whether people
are ready for it you know like I could
be really vulnerable and in this record
talk about all of my really deep dark
shadows the kind of things that I don't
tell anyone about and I think that would
probably wouldn't go down well with most
people and I would destroy my reputation
and so in a political environment there
is a reason why we we keep to a script
the script is and reference to what the
collective super-ego decides is normal
and okay and and so what I'm sitting
with is whether you know vulnerability
which has become this trend in you know
the kind of the the Brene brown and
zeitgeist in spiritual circles whether
it has what how no how does that relate
to politics so it's only to say that
that's I would love if you had a yeah
I'm glad you brought that up because
because I had a resistance to you
speaking of you know a couple times
about vulnerability without also
speaking about toughness because again I
I think it's this emphasis on the
feminine so we have to be tough and
vulnerable I think I mean and toughness
might not be you know that in vogue but
and you know I don't Varner ability is
not necessarily a a confession it might
just be not be stepping out of the mask
right the persona and just just being
there right you know being really really
there you know which you can feel so you
can be on the script or off the script
that's that's not really the point the
is is the language of languaging or the
words it's it's it's the presence behind
the language in the words because words
are limited
hmm and I think that's a I think that
that's maybe my sense is that that's
what people are yearning for is to feel
the presence of public figures to be
able to feel them and in a way Trump is
a facsimile of that you he is very
visceral he does depart from the script
and you do feel him but maybe there's a
question around whether that's actually
coming from an authentic presence inside
ember from something else well it's it's
he's like the ugliest man in the world
which is kind of interesting like its
cousin because it's like to see that
right I have a suspicion that you know
of course I don't support Trump and
practically anything that he is or says
or does but I have a suspicion that you
that the Trump is is Trump is the shadow
himself it's like coming out and that's
that's that's important that he's here
for people to see that which is not a
political statement you know of any kind
of it but it but it allows it it allows
it it's kind of smashed all the
constructions that we have puppy I
remember very feeling very much when he
was elected that the world that Mike
whatever I've constructed as my reality
is no longer that that's it's no longer
the same it's something it's something
something different so sorry if you can
if you if you have the guts to look at
that it can be valuable right rather
than just you know being reactive
yeah even even even speaking of even
speaking of his even saying his name is
almost like it's like a curse of some
kind it's like you feel like you're
cursed right to be talking about him
like I said I remember before I selected
don't even talk about him don't say his
name to say that name is a curse it's a
curse but it's but it's but it's but
it's extremely valuable to look at that
you know that's again I'm not talking
about whatever damage he's doing or
whatever but he's he's the pathological
man
you know and he's the non man man he's
he's in that void you know that he
creates you know new things can kind of
emerge out of whatever he's destroying I
think was a radical thing to say look
well maybe I think what's missing like
on one level it's the it's the it's the
personification of the tyrannical father
and it gives people a way of localizing
a wider maybe a set of wider concerns
about that we have but it's more than
that though it's it's not just
tyrannical its ugliness I want to go
further than tyrannical it's ignorant
it's like it's like you know so I am but
you know my theory of this and you press
that this he he's the creation of
progressivism as much as he is the
creation of he's the creation of the
left and the right he's just he's just
like saying okay is this the world you
want people you know you know wait wait
wake the up I suppose maybe I'm
wondering whether you would agree with
the sense that ultimately Trump is a
mirror to all of those qualities that we
have within us and that we you know we
we are horrified by travel and yet Trump
is the Western shadow and that on all of
those tendencies lie dormant within us
if like if you know that that that would
be a you know a perspective from shadow
psychology or from Jungian psychology
that we have the you know we have the
the murderer and the rapist inside us
that potential is latent unless it is we
are conscious to complete schmuck or
whatever it could be you don't even have
to talk about it in that in that extreme
terms sort of non person right
and what do you mean by good question I
I have a feeling that Trump is a
non-person like he's not that he's not a
soul he doesn't have a soul but but
there's a lot of people but then again
there's another kind of there's another
kind of persona in politics that doesn't
have a soul either that's very flashy
and very who speaks very well and it's
like you were saying I think before that
that that you see a lot of these empty
shells walking around and and you don't
have any you don't have any feeling for
them you know at least you get a feeling
come from at least Trump makes people
feel on some level yeah which was I
think you know I mean it's a terrible
thing but it's it's good didn't what
Trump is making people feel I have good
well I'm really I think that's a good
take away from me is the your media
impression that the the overemphasis of
vulnerability and not emphasizing
toughness and that has the virtue and
that maybe that's that's kind of been a
something that has helped click into
place where vulnerability is an asset
but also if it isn't a company by
toughness then it just seems a bit too
soft and something that doesn't have
substance and you need both right and
when it really it can be very
manipulative too right
yeah I'm being vulnerable and take care
of me and I love me and look at and you
know so I don't think that's what we
mean by vulnerability though I think we
need something else I think there's a
place where vulnerability and toughness
meet and that's I think vulnerability is
toughness in a way because you have to
be tough to be vulnerable you have to
you know you have to be there well what
I just wanted me to leave you with is
that the vulnerability so that so one
interesting article I can send it on to
you afterwards is Jules evidence I don't
know if you've really with his writing
his posture in the UK and he talks about
the or he's written about the shadow
vulnerability and this idea of being a
status play within certain communities
and in being a you know way of never or
all TED Talks have the vulnerability
moment at some point oh you know it's a
marketing it's a marketing ploy to but
the genuine vulnerability you know where
you genuinely feel vulnerable you feel
like the ground beneath you isn't
sellers and that in a way that that is
the true honoring of of reality and of
the complexity of a situation and so
political leaders do us a great service
when they can be vulnerable and
acknowledge actually this this situation
that we're in doesn't conform to the
narrative that we have about us yeah
actually it's much more confusing and
complex but my question is the degree to
which the public at large has a
tolerance level of uncertainty because
it is something it's impossible you have
to work well when you say vulnerability
I I what came up for me is truth right
you know so so so you know politicians I
guess I guess that's what vulnerability
would be for a politician it would be to
risk risk telling the truth in certain
situations right where where one's
reputation might be at stake and but but
the truth would supersede the person's
reputation and and it would supersede
the you know whatever kind of you know
manipulation you know that that needs to
be done which may be idealistic but well
yeah you or the politics place but I
think one durability is true its embody
truth right I don't think it you know
and then there's you know there's a
manipulative mask of vulnerability which
can be very dangerous but then there's
real truth no no no go ahead this is
you're speaking of
a lot of what you're saying I'm curious
the degree to which she read pana rent
or her thinking and writing as
influenced you advocate as she is
someone that speaks about both the
dangers of totalitarianism but also the
function of embodied truth and sneaking
into the public forum from this place
and then happened as a renewal just
curious the degree to which yeah yeah
I've read I've really depreciated her a
little I've I've I've read more and more
of Heidegger than her lover he's not
he's not sowed I guess he I guess HANA
errant is more of a political
philosopher but but yeah the what does
their big the banality of evil or is
that a big hair big in her big phrase
the banality yeah and again that's still
a that's what we're talking about right
there's all these masks who present that
present themselves and what we're really
looking for is not the mask
they've been out the banal mask is we're
looking for the the person standing in
their truth and that's what we want to
be and that's what we long for somebody
else did to manifest for us I feels like
a good place was a great pleasure
talking to you yeah really lovely thank
you
thank you for taking the time yeah